[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
I want to work out a few examples two
examples three
examples uh not in particular order of
uh of ascending
complexity the first one is going to be
very simple the next one is going to be
more complicated and the third one is
going to be even simpler than the first
one I have my
reasons but uh the first two examples
are to show you how much easier it is to
use lr's equations and to use the formal
structure of classical mechanics that
we've learned up till now the Mindless
set of mechanical rules than to actually
sit there and try to use fals Ma for all
the parts of a system uh and juggle all
the different parts of the system and
use the fact that the that the forces on
one are equal and opposite to the forces
on the other that can often be just
incredibly complicated whereas working
out the lran is very simple usually now
there's a simple mathematical reason
when you work out fals
ma a is the second derivative with
respect the time of something that means
you have to start calculating second
derivatives you have to start
calculating accelerations and that's
often complicated much more complicated
than calculating velocities which are
just first derivatives if you can
calculate the velocity of a system you
can calculate its kinetic energy very
easily 1 12 mv^
squ if you've calculated its kinetic
energy and also its potential energy you
know the lran and from that like a
mechanical fool you can sit down and
calculate the equations of motion when
you know the equations of motion you can
put them on a computer and grind out
trajectories calculating accelerations
is harder
typically uh than what I have in mind of
course when I say calculating
accelerations is I have in mind where
you have some complicated set of
coordinates where your coordinates are
not simply rectangular coordinates some
angles some other kinds of things and
out of this you have to calculate
components of acceleration that's often
much much more complicated than just
calculating the kinetic
energy let me take the first example I'm
going to study is the simple pendulum
then we're going to do a more
complicated kind of pendulum the simple
pendulum is simple enough that with a
little bit of thought and a little bit
of cleverness you can figure out how the
forces on the pendulum Bob and then use
fals
Ma okay the compound pendulum we're
going to do is far more complicated and
would Boggle the mind of anybody trying
to use f equals ma but both of them are
relatively simple not too hard to work
out if you know L grangian you know you
L
Grans all right so let's start with the
simple
pendulum simple pendulum is just a
weight hanging whoops I don't think I
like the way I drew it let's draw it
slightly different let's draw it hanging
at an
angle all right so it's connected to the
ceiling it hangs at an
angle I assume that it's connected the
pendulum
Bob has mass m it's connected by a rigid
Rod to a pivot at the ceiling and we'll
take the rigid Rod to be so light that
its mass is not important right so all
of the mass is concentrated at the end
of the
pendulum and the angle relative to the
vertical is called Theta
all right there are two features of the
theory there are two things in the lran
potential energy and kinetic energy
potential energy is proportional to the
height above some particular point and
of course the height will depend on the
angle as the pendulum swings the height
will change and as the height changes
the potential energy changes and then
there's kinetic energy and kinetic
energy is just related to the velocity
of the pendulum Bob all right let's uh
let's
first we need to specify what the length
of the pendulum is this is the pendulum
length doesn't change it's just a
constant in this problem let's call it
r r is just a number one meter or a
meter and a half or 6 inches or whatever
it's not going to change the mass
doesn't change the only thing that
changes in this problem is Theta there
the only thing which changes with time
is Theta and we want to work out its
equations of motion all right what's the
horizontal distance here that's related
to R and it's related to
Theta thank you R sin
Theta all right since you're so smart
what's the vertical
one R cosine
Theta that's this distance here let's
calculate the components the X and Y
components of the
velocity of the mass right they're just
the time derivatives of of the vertical
and horizontal components right okay so
what is the oh incidentally if we can
now this is fine yeah let's calculate
the X component of velocity the X
component of velocity is just the time
derivative of R sin Theta R doesn't
change only s Theta changes so the X
component of velocity all right V is
equal now there's going to be two
components to it the first component is
the X component it's R times the
derivative of sin Theta that's cosine
Theta times the time derivative of theta
if I want to know the time derivative of
sin Theta I differentiate with respect
to Theta and then I multiply by the time
derivative of time derivative of theta
so that's R cosine Theta time Theta Dot
that's the X component of the Velocity
the Y component of the
Velocity I'm counting components
downward I guess uh I count distance
downward as positive in this uh in this
picture here so the vertical component
of the Velocity is the time derivative
of R cosine Theta and that's
R minus r sin of theta time Theta Dot
why minus because the derivative of
cosine is minus s so these are the two
components of the velocity of the
pendulum
Bob and now if we want
the kinetic energy we just have to write
1 12 mv^ 2 so the kinetic energy T is
just 12 the
mass times the sums of the squares of
the components of the velocity vx^ 2
plus v
y^2 okay these are components of the
Velocity in two perpendicular directions
the total velocity or the total speed is
the sums of the squares and what is that
that's going to be R
2ar Theta do
2ar times cosine theta
2ar plus s of theta
squar right each component will give an
r s and a Theta do squar in the square
of the velocity and then one of them has
cosine squar the other has sin squar but
what is cosine squar plus sin squar it's
just one so the kinetic energy is
just2 the mass * R 2 * Theta do^ 2 we
can forget cosine s+ sin squ it's just
one that's the kinetic energy of the
pendulum
Bob what about its potential energy
the potential energy is simply the
height above some particular point we
could take that point to be the
ceiling pendulum can swing around let's
take uh the potential energy to be zero
well let's see yeah let's take the
potential energy to be zero when Theta
is when the pendulum is absolutely
horizontal the point is of course it
doesn't matter at what point you choose
the potential energy to be zero only
differences of potential energy are
important and
so the uh the height of the
pendulum is minus minus because it's
hanging down
minus r cine of
theta when Theta is
zero then the height is minus r when
Theta is pi it's up on the top then the
height is plus r cosine Theta or just
plus sorry just plus r so the minus sign
is
there uh to keep track of the
fact that when Theta is
zero the energy is minimum it's down at
the bottom that's not you that's just
the height of the pendulum relative to
the pivot what's the potential energy of
a particle in a gravitational field
mg time the height so we have to
multiply this by minus
M times the uh acceleration of
gravity this is the potential
energy let's write the Lan the
lran is just
m/2 R
2 Theta do
2ar minus the potential
energy minus the potential energy the
potential energy itself has a minus in
front of it so that means we should add
mg R cosine of
theta again why plus because we want
minus the potential energy in the lran
and the potential energy has a minus
sign two minus signs make a plus
sign that's a lot easier than figure
figuring out the acceleration and using
FAL ma for the two components of motion
and then juggling them together little
Gran all we really needed to do was to
calculate the velocity as a function of
theta Dot and here it is all right what
about the equations of motion let's
write down the equations of motion first
of all we take the canonical momentum
conjugate to Theta that's Pi sub
Theta that's equal to the derivative of
Lan with respect to Theta dot that's m 2
Theta
dot it's actually the angular momentum
but we don't even need to call it that
we just call it Mr 2 Theta Dot and then
the equation of motion is that the time
derivative of this D by
DT of Mr 2 Theta dot that's the usual d
by DT of the derivative of lran with
respect to the velocity that's equal to
the derivative of the Lan with respect
to
Theta what is that that's minus
mg R sin of
theta
or we
can just write this uh we can cancel out
the masses of course and then we can
write this as r squ remember R is just a
number it doesn't vary in the problem
times Theta double dot the angular
acceleration is equal to minus gr R *
sin
Theta this can be stuck on a
computer right we just uh we either take
it as a differential equation to solve
or we break up the time axis into lots
of little intervals and do it
numerically I'm going to assume in this
course that every equation that we could
write down has a solution and that you
know how to find the solution if by
nothing else by setting it up on a
computer to simulate uh to simulate
simple differential equations like this
and it's fun to do it if you haven't
done it do it for some simple equations
of this
type
uh and this simply tells you the
acceleration as a function of the
angle so it's a usual kind of FAL ma
type
equation um let's while we're at it
let's just uh calculate the energy we
know what the energy should be the
energy should just be the kinetic energy
plus the potential energy the lran is
kinetic energy minus potential energy
but let's do it by uh by the the
Mindless method the Mindless method says
that the hamiltonian
is equal to the
momentum what did I call it Pi sub
Theta time Theta dot this is pi * Q
dot we worked that out last time minus
L what I'm writing is pi sub i q sub I
dot minus
L that's where you sum over I but
there's only one coordinate in this
problem so that's it
uh Pi sub Theta what's pi sub Theta Pi
sub Theta is m 2 Theta dot so this
becomes m 2 Theta dot time another Theta
dot Theta dot
squared that's Pi Theta dot minus the
lran so it's
minus mr^ 2 /
2 Theta do
squared minus
mg R cosine
Theta this
is these two things constitute minus
L okay so this is easy Mr 2 Theta do 2
m/ 2 r^ 2 theta. 2 uh this cancels half
of this and just turns this
into
Plus
that's the
energy hamiltonian or equivalently the
energy that's
it okay it is the kinetic energy plus
the potential energy don't get fooled by
this minus sign here potential energy
had a minus sign in
it
oh it's almost always equal to
2T yeah um doesn't have to be but it's
often uh
2 certainly if the poent if the kinetic
um if the kinetic energy is of the form
1 12 mv^ squ then it's always going to
be that way it's
it's I we can concoct some in which it's
not the case and I'll remind me but for
the simple examples It's usually the
case but don't trust it don't trust a
thing like that you you work out each
example
separately all right that's the energy
how does the pendulum move well I'm not
going to solve the equations of motion
but of course we know how it moves we
have a pretty good idea if the energy is
all right let's first of all
notice what's the difference of energy
at the bottom of the orbit and the top
the difference of the energy at the top
we would have pl we would have
mg times cosine of pi or minus that so
at the top the energy is plus
MGR and at the bottom it's minus MGR all
right so it takes some energy to get to
the top it from the bottom to the top
you have to pay a price twice
MGR if let's start let's imagine
starting the pendulum at the bottom here
with a certain velocity we give it a
poke to give it some
velocity if the velocity is not enough
if the kinetic energy at the bottom is
not enough to overcome the necessary
energy to get to the top then of course
what will happen is the pendulum will
swing up run out of kinetic energy it
has converted some kinetic energy to
potential energy but it didn't have
enough to get to the top and so it'll
start back it'll swing to the other side
and it will just endlessly oscillate
back and forth symmetrically on both
sides uh that's intuitively clear and it
actually is a feature of the
equations
um just endless
oscillation almost like a harmonic
oscillator which is system we're going
to study
shortly but a little more
complicated yeah
what's
that no Theta is pi at the
top Pi is 180
degrees oh no no no I see what you mean
no no I'm sorry okay the top doesn't
mean when it's uh
when I'm imagine good I'm imagining a
pivot point and uh the pendulum swings
around 360 deges around the pivot point
so the top means up here good point
okay yeah
well right yes no that uh that's right
what I meant by the top of the orbit was
when the pendulum is vertically upright
okay and uh above the
ceiling okay what if it does have enough
energy to climb to the Top If it has
enough kinetic energy at the bottom so
that by the time it gets to the top it
still has a little bit of uh kinetic
energy left over in other words if its
kinetic energy to begin with is a little
bit bigger than 2
MGR then it will have kinetic energy to
spare when it gets to the top and it
will just keep going and it'll cycle
around going faster at the bottom
slowing down going over the top and just
endlessly round and round and round and
round so there are two kinds of
orbits two kinds of motions really
strictly speaking
three uh there's oscillation back and
forth and there's uh what should we call
it
um I don't
know yeah um
hot rot kind of rotating motion to the
left and a rotating motion to the right
of course you can ask what happens if it
has exactly enough energy to get to the
top well then it'll just go to the top
and sit at the top but that's uh that's
highly uh fine-tuned and not the sort of
thing you're likely to
encounter so we'll ignore that
possibility there's nothing wrong with
it just go up to the top and just get
there barely and you
stop okay those are uh that's the basic
uh the basic pendulum and as I said my
main reason for well two reasons for
illustrating it the first is just to
show you that it's easier to calculate
using Lans than it would be to f equals
ma for a system as complicated as this
but really I want to show you another
system which is the double Pendulum The
Double pendulum is a far more
complicated system it has very very
complicated motions its motions are
chaotic we haven't learned what chaos
means yet we will
but its motions are chaotic and truly
baffling if you watch the uh the Double
pendulum and if you were to try to study
it by using just f equals ma without
knowing the lran formulation of it you
would spend hours working out its
equations of
motion it's too complicated for it would
certainly be too complicated for me to
do on the
Blackboard but if you know how to
calculate L Grans it's just mechanical
here's what the double pendulum is again
a pivot
point pendulum hangs from
it same deal as before it has length R
and mass m I won't bother writing its
mass but then connected to this pendulum
there's another
one I'll also for Simplicity give it
radius r and to keep it simple I'll give
it the same mass as the first one okay
it's also in a gravitational
field this one swings while the first
one swings and the whole thing is a
really complicated uh mechanical
system and it's even complicated just to
work out its equations of motion except
yes the same plane yeah in the same
plane now the we could could do it more
generally no good big problem about
doing it more generally but I'll take
the case where they're in the same plane
you could have asked that up there
too is a uh is it a planer pendulum or
is it a pendulum that can swing out in
uh in all directions I chose to do the
the planer pendulum it might be fun to
work out the equations for the full
three-dimensional pendulum which can
swing out of the Blackboard but I won't
do that here in fact it's easy enough we
could do it here but uh we won't all
right let's give it some coordinates the
first thing that you do when you see a
problem like this is to Define some
coordinates all right a little bit of
experience will teach you what the best
choice of coordinates is and if you
don't choose the best choice that's okay
too I mean uh just pick a set of
coordinates and a set of coordinates
means those things which determine the
position of the system a minimal number
of objects which determine the position
of the object all right the first
coordinate is of course
Theta the angle that the first pendulum
makes relative to the
vertical Now you kind of have a choice
you could take for the second
pendulum you could
take the angle that the second pendulum
makes with respect to the location of
the first pendulum we could call it
fi or we could take the angle of the
second pendulum with respect to the
vertical
six of one half a dozen of the other I
chose in my my
notes to use the angle relative to the
vertical all right so this I call Fi and
that's it if you know Theta and you know
fi you know the location of the uh of
the
pendulum
completely now we need to calculate the
kinetic and potential energy right so
let's first first calculate the kinetic
energy of the first bar over
here okay it's exactly the same no
difference uh the calculation is
identical once again this is our sin
Theta and so forth I can just write down
the answer for the first piece of it
it's just 12 M Theta R sorry 12 m r
2 Theta
squar that's the kinetic energy of the
first Bob but what about the second one
well the second one is moving for two
reasons one of them is that the first
Bob is moving and if the first Bobb is
moving even if the angle five were not
changing the second Bob would move so we
have to add two velocities together to
get the velocity the components of
velocity of the second Bob to get the
compon or
uh
yeah the components of velocity of the
second Bob are the sum of the Velocity
as if this was standing still
plus the component of motion of the
first Bob I'll write down the answer and
you'll see why it is I think you won't
have much trouble seeing why it is the
velocity of the second Bob let's give it
some components here it is velocity of
the second B
it has two
components
sorry B3 plus three well I don't know
why you call it interacting but you can
you call it whatever you
want
uh oh the fact that it's attached to
this one yeah we can also
we we can also call these things
whatever we want I call them Bob you
could call them Herman it doesn't matter
but uh we could call him Bob and this
one Herman I like that this one's Bob
this one's Herman okay so here's Bob's
kinetic energy and Herman's kinetic
energy has or Herman's velocity has two
components let's of course has two
components but each component itself
consists of two parts right so the X
component of motion the X component of
Herman's velocity will consist of the X
component the Bob's velocity that is
where is it R cosine
Theta times Theta
Dot and then the component of Herman
relative to Bob pretend Bob is standing
still what would be the X component of
Herman's motion well it'll be exactly
the same as Bob's except instead of
theta put fi
if Bob was standing still and Herman
were oscillating or or swinging then we
would add to this plus
r cosine of f time F
dot that's the X component of motion two
pieces to it one associated with the
fact that Bob moves that's this one and
the other associated with the fact that
Herman moves relative to Bob now what
about the Y component exactly the same
thing Bob has some y motion and Herman
has some y motion relative to Bob
exactly the same so the this is the X
component comma and the Y component
would be Rus R sin Theta Theta
dot minus r s of f time F
Dot
are there any questions about what I've
written
down all I've done was treat Herman as
if he were a pendulum of exactly the
same kind substituting the angle fi
wherever I saw
Theta in the first
calculation good now we can calculate
the kinetic energy we know the
components here's the kinetic energy of
Bob here's the components of velocity of
Herman let's calculate Herman uh kinetic
energy let's do it over here Herman's
kinetic energy is 12 M same velocity
sorry same mass now we have to square
this and add it to the square of this
this is the X component here's the Y
component what do we get let's let's
look at let's see if we can examine it
and see what we get we're going to get
r^ 2 cine Theta 2 Theta do squared when
we Square the X component we'll square
this and we'll square and we'll add to
it the square of the Y component so
we're going to get this squared plus
this squared what does that give us that
gives us R 2 cine 2 + sin s that's 1 *
Theta do^
2 okay so that's just going to be 12 m r
2 Theta do^ 2
all I've done is said that when I Square
VX and I Square v y and add them
together it gives me a term with a
cosine squared and a term with a s
squared all right those add together to
just give Theta do squar then we have
the same thing over here that's going to
do exactly the same
thing
plus 12 m r 2 5 do s
that's coming from the square of this
piece plus the square of this piece cine
5^ 2 plus sin 5^ 2 also adds to one what
have I left
out I've left out the cross terms this
times this and this times this
okay okay so let's add them in we have
Plus of
course
um well it's 12 M again 12
m r
2ar times two there's always a two when
a plus b^ 2 has 2 a so there's a two
that'll eat up this two in the
denominator it'll give us a Theta dot
times a f dot oh that's something new
Theta dot time F
dot this is the first time we've seen
velocities coming in multiplying each
other so Theta do time F dot there's m r
2 and then there's cosine Theta cosine
of
pi but there's also a term from the
cross term from V1 from the Y component
that's going to be exactly the same
except that it will have sin Theta * sin
5 instead of
cosine so there's plus sin
Theta sin
th this looks to me like the kinetic
energy of Herman which I now add to the
kinetic energy of Bob to get the total
kinetic
energy that just takes this factor of a
half away removes the factor of a half
just doubles this term involving Theta
dot squ the fact that it just doubled it
was because of a special choice of the
fact that I took the same radius Vector
the same radius here and the same mass
in general it would just do something
else wouldn't just double it but I chose
the numbers simply so that it would just
do something nice and simple and that's
it now what about cosine Theta time
cosine 5 plus sin Theta time sin 5
anybody recognize
that yes so what is
it
uhuh cosine of theta minus
F okay this is cosine of theta minus
F cine Theta minus 5 I hate putting
brackets inside parentheses inside
parentheses I'll just put an underline
here to indicate that these are grouped
together oh no we can I guess we don't
know we can we can
uh we can spare our parentheses
there that's
it is it surprising that it's cosine of
theta minus 5 not really and I'll tell
you why supposing we didn't have the
gravitational field here Al together
supposing there was no preferred
Direction the preferred Direction in
this problem is the vertical Direction
due to the uh the gravitational field if
there was no
um uh preferred Direction the problem
would have a symmetry the Symmetry would
be rotation symmetry where you rotate
both Theta and F
simultaneously if you just rotated the
whole thing and so you kind of expect
that the lran should not change if you
added to Theta and fi the same angle
that would would just be rotating
everything now that is more or less
obvious when you think about it if you
just took the whole configuration and
rotated it the uh the lran shouldn't
change and that's what tells you that
only angle differences should come in
here an angle difference doesn't change
if you add to both Theta and fi the sum
of the angles would
change if I added two degrees to Theta
and I added two degrees to fi then theta
plus fi would get added four degrees but
Theta minus 5 wouldn't change at all so
there's a symmetry to this problem in
the absence of the potential energy if
we don't have a potential energy
associated with the gravitational field
of the earth then the problem has a
symmetry and the Symmetry we'll work it
out later we're going to work out the
conserved quantity that's associated
with it it is of course some form of
angular momentum them but before we do
that let's work out the potential
energy
yes oh yes good all right so from Herman
we had a one half mg sorry one
half Bob and Herman conspired to get rid
of the
half what's
that no
no no no
no yeah I added Bob together with
Herman Herman also had an MR 2 theta. s
and
so
good
um good so that's uh that's the kinetic
energy what about the potential energy
well this is
T kinetic
energy potential energy that's exactly
the same as it was for the single
pendulum except we have to add up a
contribution for both the bobs for for
Bob and Herman excuse me all right for
Bob it's minus
mg cosine
Theta and then for Herman it's another
minus
mg cosine of
F cosine yeah cosine of F R thank you mg
R cosine
Theta right so the total lran we now
have the lran and it
is Mr 2 Theta do^ 2 that's more or less
familiar looking except for the factor
of a half which is usually
there plus now we have a truly familiar
looking term Mr 2 5 do^
2 then we have this extremely odd cross
term which multiplies Theta do * 5
dot m r
2 Theta do F dot time cosine of theta
minus
5 then we have to subtract U so that
gives us
plus
MGR cosine of theta plus cosine of
f what's
that yeah
um right
uh
yeah
um
no no no
no
uh yes thank
you this one right yeah that one
yeah
right okay
now this is complicated I'm not going to
solve it uh what I will do is write down
some of the equations of motion but
before I do it let's work out the
conserved quantity why is there a
conserved quantity no sorry there is not
a conserved quantity because the special
Direction associated with gravity means
that there's no rotational symmetry of
this problem this problem does not have
a conserved quantity altogether which
makes it about as complicated as a
simple system like this can be but if we
forgot gravity I don't mean if we forgot
it I mean if we did this way way out in
space where there was no gravitational
field it would still be a rather
complicated
problem but it would have a new feature
of having a
symmetry this would not be there let's
get rid of it and then there would be a
symmetry what would the Symmetry be the
symmetry of course would be rotation
where you add to each angle exactly the
same amount so it's Theta goes to theta
plus Epsilon where Epsilon is a small
angle and five goes to five plus
Epsilon same angle you can't shift one
by one thing and the other one by
another thing you shift them both by the
same
amount remember the last time we defined
symmetries so that Q went to Q Plus
Epsilon time f F of
Q this just means that the fs are both
equal to
one okay the fs which I defined last
time that go along that tell you how a q
changes when you perform the Symmetry
transformation in this case they're both
the same okay can we see in fact that
the L grangian doesn't change when you
do this well if you add a constant to a
Theta if you add a constant to something
you don't change its time derivative so
you don't change the Theta do squ you
don't change the f Do squ by adding a
constant and you don't change cosine of
theta minus F because Theta minus F
doesn't change at all so in fact this
lran has the Symmetry I don't know would
you say we've discovered it or imposed
it I think we discovered it but of
course we imposed it by getting rid of
the gravitational
field so it's a bit of both all right
let's calculate the angular momentum or
the conserved quantity the nther charge
and see what it is which doesn't change
with time if we know that something
doesn't change with time that goes a
long way toward helping us solve a
problem it takes a problem involving two
variables and really replaces it with a
problem with only one
variable it diminishes the number of
equations since we know that something
doesn't change with time okay so let's
see if we can figure it out the rule is
the ner the charge is pi sub i q sub I
sorry Pi sub
I
times what I called f sub I summ over
I where Pi sub
I is partial of the lran with respect to
qabi Dot
and what about Fs subi in our case the
fs are just one so this just
becomes Pi sub theta plus pi sub
F not to surprising it's just the sum of
the canonical momenta of theta and F why
because the fs are both equal to one but
now we have to calculate what pi sub
Theta and Pi subf are you might expect
that Pi
Theta is just related to Theta Dot and
you might expect that Pi fi is just
related to fi dot but it's more
complicated because of this mixed term
here so let's calculate them Pi sub
Theta is equal to the derivative of the
lran with respect to Theta
dot all right what is
that uh it
has
here's Theta dot over
here m 2 Theta Dot and a factor of two
when you differentiate Theta do squar
you get twice Theta
dot partial of L with respect to Theta
dot has twice Mr R 2 Theta dot but we're
not finished there's this mixed term
here there's a Theta D in it so there's
a plus m²
F dot * cosine of thetus
5 that's Pi sub Theta what about Pi subf
same
game all right Five
Dot looks very similar the first term
except it doesn't have the two in front
of it because of the half which appears
in lrin instead of the two appearing in
pi we just have m r 2 F dot this is
partial of L with respect to F dot but
then we also have a term from here plus
m r 2 now it's Theta
dot time cosine of theta minus
5 look how odd it's gotten Pi sub Theta
involves F Dot and Pi subf involves
Theta
dot so things have gotten a little mixed
up not to worry we just we just uh
nevertheless follow our nose
mechanically add these things
together I won't bother well I will
write out the answer the answer is 2m 2
Theta dot plus m 2 F dot I think think
I'm missing an r m r 2 here right plus m
2 Theta
dot plus F
dot time cosine of theta minus
5 this is the thing which doesn't change
with time we can call it the angular
momentum it's the thing which is
conserved because of rotation Symmetry
and it doesn't change with time it gives
us a piece of information if we know the
angular momentum at any given time let's
say at the start of the at the start of
the trajectory then it stays fixed
Forever
After and allows us to figure out what
Theta dot is in terms of f dot it allows
us to eliminate one of the variables of
the
problem
okay only one variable allows us to to
eliminate one thing
uh and simplifies the equations for us
but as you can see the main reason for
doing
this was to show you how mechanical it
is to calculate the lran to calculate
the conserved quantity and then to
calculate the equations of motion let's
do the equations of
motion it's it's boring it's it's quite
boring anything which has been reduced
to being mechanical like this is
naturally going to be
boring and that's the goal of physics to
make everything really
boring okay oh this is this is not the L
grangian here this is the angular
momentum let's not confuse it with that
L up
there okay so let's calculate the
equations of
motion we've calculated Pi let's just do
theta I won't do fi we'll just do theta
the first thing is to calculate d by DT
of partial of L with respect to Theta
dot okay that's already a little bit
complicated but it's straightforward d
by
DT of what is it 2m r
s Theta
dot that's just got Theta second
derivative Theta double dot right m r 2
they're constants then there's Plus
what's the other
term
H what
question I heard somebody say double
dot this is double dot d by DT of theta
dot is Theta double dot right all right
uh but this is not the full Pi sub Theta
the rest of Pi sub Theta has this term
so it has another Mr s again Mr squ is a
constant then it has F
Dot and then cosine of theta minus
5 all right this is a little bit
complicated d by DT of this term just
gives us Theta double dot d by DT of
this term is a little bit complicated we
have to differentiate F dot time cosine
of theta minus 5 you know how to do that
I'm not going to waste your time it'll
give us a five double dot term and then
it'll give us a term where the time
derivative hits the cosine here I'll let
you do that straightforward calculus
it'll give you a few more terms than you
might have expected
so on the left side we have d by DT of
uh of a very definite quantity we can
feed this into a
computer calculate Five Dot at each
instant along a trajectory differentiate
it and all of this can be worked out
easily and that's equal to what that's
equal to the derivative of the lran with
respect to Theta itself that's equal to
DL by D Theta that's lr's
equations where does Theta appear the
okay
yeah yes it is yes it
is well you just following Knows Why
yeah the derivative with respect to one
of them is minus the derivative with
respect to the other it's
true whenever you have a function of a
difference of two variables the
derivative with respect
to yeah you'll pick up a minus sign when
you differentiate this with respect to
fi you'll get a minus sign from over
here okay yeah yeah okay
um so I assume assum you know how to do
this derivative on the left on the right
the only place where Theta appears is in
this cosine here okay
so
yeah yeah yeah yeah you'll get one term
with a Theta Dot and another term with a
f Dot and they'll have opposite sign
right okay so I'll leave that to you uh
there's nothing terribly interesting
straightforward
calculus and the other thing which is
here is the right hand side which is the
derivative of the lran with respect to
Theta and that is just equals Mr
2 uh F
Dot and then the derivative of cosine
Theta sorry the derivative of cosine
with respect to Theta just becomes minus
s of theta minus
five can everybody read this I
can't
yeah oh
Mr 2 5 dot time
the upstairs how how much higher
oh oh you're right thank you thank you
thank you thank you thank
you uh very good yes the derivative of
the lran with respect the Theta so
that's going to give me what another
five uh Theta dot yeah yeah thank you
good
but it's mechanical the point is it's
mechanical it's complicated the final
answer is complicated but mechanical no
uh no ambiguities in the steps right
this is the equation of motion for the
double pendulum the Theta equation you
can work out the F equation in the
absence of a gravitational field it's
already complicated one of them spinning
around is exchanging energy back and
forth and angular momentum back and
forth with the other it's a rather
complicated motion that these things
undergo even in the absence of the
gravitational field but the one thing
that you have going for you when there's
no gravitational field is you have a
conserved quantity that you can use to
replace Theta dot by its expression in
terms of f
dot you also have energy conservation
right right that effectively eliminates
one whole uh degree of freedom and right
you have energy conservation so you can
fix the energy and you can fix the
angular momentum and that is effectively
two equations that allow you to
eliminate let's say we can eliminate F
Dot and fi out of the equation and just
have an equation for Theta all right but
we're not we're not in the business of
solving equations here we're in the
business of studying the formal
structure of mechanics and as I said the
main reason for doing this ton
was to show you that a problem which is
very very treacherously tricky when you
try to think about it in terms of f
equals Ma and it would take us a lot
longer to do on the Blackboard you
simply set up what you have to do the
rules are figure out the velocity Square
it write 1 12 mv^ squar figure out the
potential energy subtract it off and
then you're going you're uh you're on
your
way
okay
all right I said I would take a simple
problem
pendulum then a complicated problem the
double
pendulum we'll come back to the double
pendulum when we talk about chaos a
little bit the double pendulum is a very
chaotic system which means it's rather
unpredictable despite the fact that the
equations of motion are in some sense
exactly predictable it does some rather
unusual and weird motions we'll come
back to it as an example of Chaos uh but
for now it was just an example of the
canonical uh or the lran formulation
what is the incidentally what is the um
the energy of the system well all the
terms with Theta dots are kinetic energy
the term without the Theta dots of
potential
energy for a system like this the energy
is
simply the kinetic energy plus the
potential energy instead of minus so you
would just change the sign of this term
I think that's
right
uh so in that sense it's similar to the
ordinary
pendulum all right the next problem that
I want to
study is the most basic problem of all
of theoretical
physics it's the one that comes up over
and over and over again what is
it harmonic ill there's one problem
which is a little bit simpler than the
harmonic oscillator a little more
fundamental I fundamental a little uh
and it's of course just the free motion
of a free particle with no forces on it
that's really
boring the harmonic oscillator is a
boring problem but not quite as
boring uh By Boring I mean of course
that the motion is so simple and so
completely predictable that
uh uh it has no
surprises but it does have a structure a
mathematical structure and a
uh uh which is which underpins so much
of physics that we need to get it right
from the
beginning the
pendulum is almost a version of the
harmonic
oscillator if you look at the pendulum
and you displace it just a little bit
from the origin It swings back and forth
very very much much like an ordinary
harmonic
oscillator if you displace it far from
the origin then it's not quite true the
mathematical connection is as follows
the potential energy minus MGR cosine
Theta what does that look like let's
let's draw a picture of it just minus
cosine Theta cosine of theta looks like
this
right from 0 to 2 pi swing all the way
around minus the cosine which is what's
in the potential energy looks like
this so it's minimum at it's minimum at
theta equals
zero in other words the energy is
minimum when it's hanging straight down
okay that's uh that's the expression for
the energy I could continue it back a
little bit to negative values of
theta and it's minimum right
here any function which is minimized at
a point
has a basic feature that its first
derivative is zero right what comes next
is the second
derivative any function like this which
has a minimum is well approximated by a
parabola at the bottom in other words by
something proportional to Theta
squared this is approximately equal to
high Precision when Theta is small in
fact to to correct the second order in
Theta it's equal to
mg well let's get it straight it's minus
MGR which is just a
constant and not
interesting
plus 12 mg R Theta
squar I'm simply using the fact that
near the bottom of the orbit like this
you can approximate this curve by a
parabola
something proportional to Theta
squar any function which has a minimum a
smooth minimum like this typically will
be approximated by a
parabola well that's not quite true it
could be flatter than a parabola but
that would be an exceptional
situation but typically when a function
has a minimum at the minimum you can
approximated by something proportional
to Theta squ if you did
so and you ignored the constant in the
energy which doesn't uh which is of no
particular
importance did I get this wrong did I
get the sign right here let's say U is
yeah U is plus then we would have in the
lran
minus 12 MGR Theta
squar and in the energy we would have
plus but the important thing here is
that it's just proportional to Theta
squar it's a very simple expression the
simplest expression you can imagine for
the kinetic energy about a minimum about
a point of minimum energy something
quadratic that's what defines the
harmonic oscillator when
the energy or the potential energy is
simply quadratic in the coordinate
that's called a harmonic oscillator all
right so let's uh let's instead of
calling the coordinate Theta let's call
it X here's another system that we might
study an object on a spring with a mass
m it the spring has some equilibrium
position some natural length when it's
stretched and not under any stress when
it's not stretched or compressed and if
you compress it or you stretch
it the mass will oscillate about the
equilibrium
point the if we call xal Z the
equilibrium point in other words let's
call this the x axis and take x equal to
Z at the equilibrium point then we have
to do some work to stretch it we have to
do some work to compress it and the
potential energy is proportional to X
squ the potential energy in this case is
proportional to x^2 with a constant
coefficient
K and it's conventional to put a two
there this is called the spring constant
the spring constant kx^ 2 uh and there
by convention we put a two
there
yeah uh I just dropped it because a
constant doesn't do anything but you're
right it's there but it wouldn't make
any difference to anything the reason is
because it's a
constant and the only things which come
into equations of motion are derivatives
of the lran that will not contribute
anything to the derivatives of the lran
so you're right there is another term
here it's a constant term and just
ignore it because it doesn't uh it
doesn't affect
anything okay so for a simple system
like a spring a good approximation is to
say that the potential energy is
positive you increase the energy by
stretching the spring you also increase
the energy by compressing the spring in
either direction you have to work to
move the spring K x^2 / 2 the fact that
there's a numerical number there that's
not surprising the two is simply a
matter of definition K over2 is called
is the uh coefficient um in the in the
energy the
lran is then 12
mv^2 minus
k/2
x^2 what about the force on the
oscillator what about the force remember
that
force is equal to minus the derivative
of potential with respect to X and
that's equal to minus
KX the derivative of this with respect
to X is just KX force is equal to minus
KX the minus sign means that the force
is a restoring Force if you stretch so
that X becomes positive the force is
negative pulls you back if you compress
so that X is negative the force is
positive and again it's a restoring
Force so this is the L grangian
uh the force being proportional to X has
a name it's called Hook's law how do you
spell hook h o k with it two o's e all
right I wasn't sure if there was an e at
the end I didn't remember Hook's law
this is Hook's
law Hook was Newton's best
friend so this is your Standard
Spring mathematically idealized the real
spring of course would have a more
complicated uh formula in fact if you
stretch the real spring enough it would
break so there's all sorts of
complicated nonlinearities in it this is
an idealization and it's good for small
excursions of the
spring
no no of course not you can't dve hooks
law you can only uh experimentally
measure it but what you can
say is
that on mathematical
grounds
um a function which has a
minimum has no first derivative if it
has no first derivative that means
there's no term proportional to x a
constant is irrelevant we don't care
about a constant in the energy next
there could be a term proportional to X
but if we're at the minimum then the
derivative of the function with respect
to X is zero and the first order correct
Direction the first order term is zero
the next term is proportional to
x2 in other words if we expanded a
function in a tailor series expansion in
powers of X the first term could be a
constant which we're not interested in
the next term would be X proportional to
X but if we're sitting at the minimum
then there's no slope X would mean a
slope there is no slope so that's not
there then there's x s and then there's
all the higher terms that could be there
constant x cubed another constant C
Prime X to 4th and so forth the point is
that if x is all right the main
assumption there's also a constant here
let's call it D I've already used C and
C Prime it's conceivable to think of a
function which begins with Order X cubed
in other words where the constant
multiplying X squ is just plain
zero that was would be rather special
it's usually deemed to be a fine tuning
of some sort that there would be no
quadratic term it's not a fine tuning to
say there's no linear term it's just a
statement that we start at the bottom
wherever the bottom is that there would
be no quadratic term would require some
careful tuning of a function if there's
a quadratic term that's the first thing
next would be cubic quartic and so forth
these terms are not hooks law
right but the point is that if x is
small enough that if we only deviate a
little bit from the origin then X cubed
and X4 are much much smaller than x s so
for small
displacements these terms can typically
be ignored unless the first term is
absent if the X squ term is absent then
you have to begin with X cubed but if
the first term is Not absent then for
sufficiently small
oscillations
it always begins with order x s so in
that sense hooks law is
derivable in the sense of an
approximation for small
oscillations under the circumstances
where nobody carefully fine-tuned away
the first term here hook lore is very
general this is the reason this is the
fundamental reason that the harmonic
oscillator shows up in so many
places it's always there when you're
oscillating about the minimum of a
potential energy unless somebody has uh
very carefully fine-tuned away the first
uh the first order correction the first
order
contribution second order contribution
yeah no no no no if there's a term of
order C cubed reality no of course
not no springs break if you stretch them
too
much
no it's always right it's it's always an
approximation on the one hand but it
becomes a better and better
approximation as the oscillations are
smaller and
smaller so you imagine studying this
very very small
oscillations very small oscillations it
becomes progressively more and more
exact
okay it becomes a better and better
approximation as the oscillations become
smaller and smaller of course as the
oscillations get smaller and smaller
they get less and less interesting you
can't see them after a point they're too
small uh so you have a highly accurate
theory of something which is too small
to to be
measurable uh the question the real
question is where does this term come in
compared to
this and what what is the nature of your
experiment how big are the
oscillations and is this term important
relative to this when the oscillations
have a certain
size so it becomes a question of
estimating the relative
importance of X cubed relative to X squ
and that depends on the size of these
coefficients but for almost all systems
for sufficiently small
oscillations in other words sufficiently
small energy the x squ is usually a good
approximation the linear
term if we put a linear term in let's
put a linear term in okay uh give me
another letter
uh k k I've already used K over here I
don't want to a ax what would this do
well it would put a first derivative
over here it would mean that the
function now has a first derivative and
it would look like
this well that would just mean that you
started at the wrong
Point instead of starting at this point
start at this
point shift x shift the definition of X
so that x equals z at this point and
then there won't be a linear
term yeah okay
so uh uh the X the constant coefficient
is of no importance a constant the
linear term can always be shifted by
going to the
minimum by starting your calculate by
starting your coordinates at the minimum
that's gets rid of the first term and
then you're left with the X squ term
right all right so as I said in that
sense it's a rather General structure
which is always a good approximation for
sufficiently small oscillations it
always breaks down when the oscillations
get big enough whatever they are they
are whether they are light oscillations
sound oscillations water waves um uh
Springs vibrating for very small
oscillations hooks low is a good
approximation for large oscillations it
breaks
down the pendulum is a perfectly good
example what comes after Theta squar if
you expand cosine
Theta Theta to the 4th there's a Theta
it happens there's no Theta Cub term
there's a Theta to the fourth term so uh
if you take large swings the large
swings are sensitive to the higher terms
in the cosine but for small enough
swings only the Theta squ term is
important all right yeah that
equation this
one I've lost track of it let's
see
um uh you are
right yeah
yeah I think that I think you're right
yeah sounds right
no I
was yeah but cosine has 1 minus uh Theta
squ over two you put the when you were
talking about changing yeah right yeah
no I I think it's
minus measured from theta equals z the
potential energy is positive if the
potential energy is positive then in Lan
it should be
negative all right this
the importance of this
system I've explained why it's important
why it recurs over and over in
physics now we have to understand it we
have to study its properties it's
hamiltonian it's leian its equations of
motion and all the things that
uh that we've learned up till now apply
them to this
system
yeah say it
again MO is
near
in other words if the system is
Disturbed only a little
bit
yeah yeah yeah for the simple
one-dimensional system or systems more
generally than that it's energy
conservation which prevents the
oscillations from getting too big you
have only a certain amount of energy
let's write down the energy the
energy
H is m/ 2x do^ 2+ k/2
x^2 all
right a large Excursion a large x will
mean a lot of energy if you only have a
small amount of energy this simply can't
get too big because it's positive if it
was negative
if you studied the system with a
negative term in the potential energy
then x dot can get big and X can get big
and cancel each other and keep the
energy
bounded it's because both these terms
are positive X do^ squ and x^ squ
neither one of them can get big if the
initial energy is small so that's a very
good
question and there's a very good answer
energy
conservation it wouldn't work if the
potential was upside
down potential being upside down means
you're standing at the top of a hill if
you displace the thing a little bit it
will go flying off the hill and your
approximation of a small oscillation
will not be
consistent
right
all right so this this is a
system worth exploring since it comes up
so
much here it is I'll write it over
again let's work out its equation of
motion we could of course just write
fals ma for this case I mean for this
case it's simple enough we can just
write F FAL ma but let's not do it that
way d l by DX dot that's Pi
subx d l by DX dot is just MX dot just
the ordinary
momentum d by DT of
that that's derivative of the L grangian
with that's d by DT of DL by DX Dot
that's the left hand side of lres
equations the right hand
side is just DL by
DX that's this so that's Min -
k/2 *
2x this of course is just good old fals
ma MX dot is equal to minus KX hooks
law it's nice to divide by the mass
let's divide by the mass
here notice the only thing which comes
into the motion is the combination K
Over
M K Over m is the important
quantity if I were to change K and
change M keeping K Over M fixed the
equation of motion would not
change all right this is a this is a an
equation whose
solution uh is well
known everybody know what it is anybody
not know what it
is it's cosiness cosiness and
signs uh corresponding to just an
oscillation let's why is it cosiness and
signs supposing I take a function like
cosine of
T and I differentiate it once then I get
S what happens if I oh sorry what do I
get if I differentiate
cosine minus s and then if I
differentiate
again minus cosine so the second
derivative of a cosine is proportional
to
itself but with a minus sign now let's
not uh cosine T is not quite right
cosine Omega t is a better bet where
Omega is the angular frequency the num
just a number okay it tells you how fast
the oscillation is oscillating Omega the
bigger Omega is the faster the
oscillation is the angle this is just
called the frequency of the
oscillation what is the first derivative
of this with respect to
time
again minus Omega sin Omega T what's the
second
derivative minus Omega 2 cosine Omega T
so if I call this
x then this is X double dot and notice
that it's just - Omega 2 *
X that's what this equation says it says
the second time derivative is
proportional to X itself with a
coefficient k/ M same minus sign and so
we identify that the frequency of the
oscillator is K Over M or frequency
squared Omega squar equals K Over
M or Omega the frequency is square root
of K Over
M supposing instead of putting cosine
there I put
s same thing if I differentiate S I get
cosine if I differentiate cosine again I
get minus the sign so this would also
work for s in fact it will work for any
combination
any linear
combination X is equal to a Time cine
Omega
t plus b * sin Omega
T any function of this form will satisfy
this equation if Omega is equal to theun
of k n you can check that each one
separately done and if you add them
together they
do why are there two coefficients why
are there two any A and B will work why
are there two coefficients in the
solution right it's because you have to
specify two things to start a solution
out one way of saying it is you have to
say you have to specify a position and a
velocity so there are two parameters
that govern a solution there have to be
in every solution of a simple equation
second order equation there have to be
two constants for each one of the
coordinates okay the general solution
one to fix the initial condition the
initial position and the other to fix
the initial
velocity you can work out A and B if you
know the initial position and the
initial velocity so this is all the
solutions there are there are no other
Solutions Beyond this there's another
way to write it you can also write it as
X is equal to a time cine of Omega * T
minus t where
T is just some constant some constant
starting
time again it has two parameters an
amplitude let's call it capital A an
amplitude of oscillation which tells you
how big the oscillations
are and a particular
time which is the time when the
oscillation reaches its maximum
in other words you can either write the
general solution in this form with two
coefficients A and B or in this form
with a coefficient that's called the
amplitude and this one is called the
phase in this form T
not is the time at which the oscillation
reaches its
maximum all right so or if you like the
starting point if you imagine stretching
the spring and letting it go
stretching it to a maximum and letting
it go the time that you let it go is
this T over
here uh when T is equal to T the cosine
is at its maximum
value so these are the two forms that
the general solution
takes
uh and it's perfectly obvious why it's
called a harmonic oscillator well I
don't know why it's called harmonic but
it's called an oscillator because it
oscillates it vibrates it vibrates with
a cosine of Omega
T all right that of course is no doubt
familiar to most of
you say it
again the phase is
t0
yeah
right so there two parameters two
parameter family of
solutions uh which as I said you can
either take to be
uh the theorem of course is that if you
add a sign and a cosine like this it's
always equal to a cosine of a shifted uh
of a shifted um
argument all right that's the basic uh
setup for the harmonic
oscillator but now we want
to think about its hamiltonian first and
its canonical
momenta canonical
momentum first of all this P which is
the same as Pi subx which is the same as
the derivative of the lorian with
respect to x
dot and what is it it's just MX dot it's
just good old
momentum nothing surprising there after
all it is just a particle on the end of
a
spring so that's p p or
Pi how about the hamiltonian let's work
out the hamiltonian the
hamiltonian is PX
dot our usual thing canonical momentum
time velocity minus the
lran minus
L and that's let's see p what's is MX
dot so PX dot is MX do^
SAR twice the kinetic energy but now
minus the lran so minus m/2 x do^
2 plus
k/2
x^2 in the
hamiltonian the KX S turn term has the
opposite sign as it had in the
lunian okay so this is exactly what you
would expect mx. 2/
2 plus k/ 2
x^2 and it's conserved for the all the
reasons that we worked out last
time we worked out that this quantity is
generally conserved so this is the
conservation of energy this is the
energy well we can write it in another
form
and now I'm going to start to teach you
about the hamiltonian formulation of qu
of of classical
mechanics up till now we've dealt with
the lran form of the equations we want
to pass now to the hamiltonian form the
hamiltonian form works not with x's and
X dots or q's and Q dots but it works
with the basic variables being canonical
momentum and coordinates q's and Pi's or
q's and
P's why why are we doing such a
thing I have to admit I have no idea why
Hamilton started thinking about things
that way the ultimate reasons boil down
to Quantum Mechanics we're not doing
quantum mechanics now we're going to do
some things which may mystify you a
little bit you'll start to get familiar
with them they're very pretty they're
elegant they're simple but what the
motivation that Hamilton had for going
along this route is is quite mysterious
I don't know what it
was nevertheless Hamilton said the
important quantities well we we'll come
to see why it's so important as we go
along but Hamilton said he wants to work
not with the quantities q and Q dot but
rather with q and P he saw some sort of
symmetry between q's and P's he saw
something very special about the
canonical momenta that's not apparent
until you start to work with it I will
tell you what it is as we go along but
the goal is to rewrite mechanics not in
terms of positions and velocities but in
terms of positions and canonical
momenta this may be this at this point
this is probably a mystery to you why
one would want to do
that and it really didn't achieve its
full um importance until quantum
mechanics so at this point you have to
hold off and say okay he's doing some
magical mystical mumbo jumbo with p's
and q's instead of q's and Q dots I
don't know why but we'll start to see as
we go along that it has
some it the form of the equations is
especially
simple it's especially simple in terms
of PS and
q's
like that yeah that's
right
yeah some people think he foresaw
quantum mechanics I don't think he saw
foresaw quantum mechanics he
just say it
again certainly is
that
well
again any system when Disturbed a little
bit from equilibrium will behave like
like an oscillator so a
molecule
um I'm not sure exactly what question
you're
asking the reason that we study
oscillators is because small deviations
from equilibrium
oate the reason is the same in quantum
mechanics as in classical mechanics but
there's a feature in quantum mechanics
which isn't there in classical mechanics
there's Zero Point Energy it's
impossible to lower the energy to an
arbitrarily small amount so the idea of
an arbitrarily small oscillation is not
sensible in quantum mechanics that
means that uh there is no real limit in
which the oscillator becomes uh per
perfectly accurate but I didn't want to
get in that now I want to keep away from
quantum mechanics until until we study
quantum
mechanics Let's uh let's move
on
the let's write the hamiltonian in terms
of p's and q's instead of q's and Q Dots
here it is here's the hamiltonian or the
energy there's the expression for the
energy here's the expression for the
canonical momentum p is MX dot to write
the hamiltonian in the form that
Hamilton would have wanted you to write
it in he would want you to get rid of
all the X dots and replace them by
P's in each case the P's will be
functions of X dots and
x's in principle you can solve for the X
dots we'll work out some examples you
can solve for the X dots
and write them in terms of P for example
in this case it's very easy x dot is
just p over
M so let's write that down x dot is p
h yeah yeah we're gonna go
that's well not
really all right so this this equation
here tells us that x dot is equal to P /
M the momentum divided by the mass is
the velocity let's plug that into
here this now reads then p^2 over
2m why is it over to
him X do2 will be P ^2 over
m^2 so when I write x. S I will have two
M's in the denominator two M's in the
denominator one m in the numerator it'll
be p^2 divided by
2m so whereas when you write the energy
in terms of velocities
the M appears in the numerator when you
write it in terms of momentum the mass
appears in the
denominator big deal but keep it in mind
that uh it's a it's a useful pneumonic
whenever you see uh something
multiplying an X do squ in a l grangian
it usually winds up that thing gets into
the denominator in the uh in the
hamiltonian plus kx^ 2 over
now notice there's a kind of symmetry in
this problem between P's and X between p
and X apart from the coefficients K and
M the hamiltonian is perfectly symmetric
between K between x's and
PS it's of the form roughly speaking of
x² + p^2 well not exactly it has some
coefficients something * p^ 2 plus
something * x^2 it has a very nice
symmetry between P's and and
x's and that symmetry is one that will
exploit over and over again that uh the
equations of hamiltonian mechanics are
entirely symmetric with respect to x's
and
PS uh they look the same uh if you
interchange X's not not exactly but the
structure of the equations is symmetric
between X and PS
but for now just recognize that the
energy has p^2 +
x^2 well not quite 1 over 2 m * p^2 + K
over2 *
x^2
let's
make a diagram representing on the
horizontal axis X and on the vertical
axis p now you could have used velocity
on the vertical
axis after all velocity and momentum are
proportional to each other but we're
going to use momentum now for now
momentum in the vertical axis horizontal
axis is um is
X
how
yeah a starting point for the motion
consists of a value of x and a value of
P
a position and a momentum so if I tell
you the position and the momentum at the
start of the motion that corresponds to
a point on the XP plane incidentally the
XP plane has a name it's called phase
space and it has a symmetry between x's
and PS that I would not have if you used
velocities on the vertical axis but
that's something that will come with
time you start the system out it starts
with a velocity in a position you can
translate the velocity into a momentum
just by dividing by the mass and so the
starting point is some point in Phase
space what happens next the system
starts to move it changes both its x's
and its PS in this case there's only one
X and 1 P the velocity changes the
position changes the system Moves In the
phase space how does it move in the
phase space can we track its trajectory
as it moves through phase space well
first of all we know that energy is
conserved that means that p^2 over 2 m +
K Over
2x^2 which is equal to the
energy call it the hamiltonian or the
energy same
thing sometimes I'll call it energy
sometimes I'll call it hamiltonian we
call it we tend to call it hamiltonian
when we're talking about its functional
form form in terms of X and P we tend to
call it energy when we're just thinking
about the numerical value of the energy
the numerical value of the energy is
conserved with time it doesn't change
and so that tells us something about the
motion can you see from this what kind
of motion it
has okay it would be a circle if M and K
were both equal to one then it would be
p^2 + x^2 is equal to 2 e or
something okay not quite a circle if you
put some coefficients in here
coefficient p^2 plus another coefficient
time X2 is equal to a constant then it's
not quite a circle what is it an
ellipse so the
motion in the phase space is elliptical
it's not a very good ellipse is
it
okay let's uh figure out the intercepts
first of all oh oh if it were a circle
in other words if M and K were adjusted
so that the coefficients here were the
same then the radius of the circle would
be controlled by e in fact e would be
the square of the radius right roughly
speaking p^2 plus X2 is equal to uh to
twice e twice e would be the square of
the radius so if we change the energy
that will change the
orbit by changing its radius now the
ellipses are all of the same exact shape
they would be circles if K and M were
one all right but they have different
distance from the origin they have
different
radi okay same shape same eccentricity
different radius different overall
radius and the radius is controlled by
the
energy so if we start the system
someplace there's an ellipse passing
through that point we take that ellipse
and the system will just continue to
move on that
ellipse let's find out where it
intersects the x- axis and the P axis it
intersects the x axis at the point where
p is zero where p is zero X let let work
it out X where p is equal to Z put it up
here k / 2 x^2 is equal to e
or X is equal to the square
root of e ided by twice e ided k I
believe twice e ided
k do I have that right yeah okay so so
the x intercept
here is square < TK of 2 e over
K notice that as e gets bigger and
bigger The Intercept moves out what
about the y or the P intercept here the
P intercept you do the same thing the P
intercept is where X is equal to zero
and we just solve for p / 2 m is equal
to e and that's p is equal to the square
otk of
2me
square root of 2 m
e so the x intercept is 2 e over K or
the square root of 2 e over K the y or
the P intercept is 2 m e square root of
that so if we know the energy and we
know the mass and we know the spring
constant we can start drawing these
ellipses in Phase space and wherever we
start the system just moves around on
the ellipse incidentally by squeezing
the x- axis and expand or by an
appropriate uh redefinition of X and P
we can turn these into circles easily
enough okay we can easily turn them into
Circles by rescaling either the x-axis
or the P axis squeeze the x-axis a
little bit or expand the P Axis or some
combination and you turn them into
circles I won't do that uh just leave it
the way it is but you can think in your
head
circles circles in Phase space
or ellipses in Phase space that can be
rescaled to
circles uh now how long does it take for
the phase point to go all the ways
around that depends on the frequency of
the oscillator
Omega the larger
Omega the long the shorter the amount of
time for it to go all the ways
around
the
all right so the fa the the phase Point
moves on
ellipses it moves around in a time which
doesn't depend on where you begin so in
other words if you actually thought of
circles think of
circles then the whole phase space
rotates around with frequency Omega
every point no matter where you begin it
takes exactly the same amount of time to
go around and so wherever you start in
this phase space you just progress
around with the same angular frequency
around and around and around wherever
you
start supposing you project the motion
onto the x- axis in other words you
don't look at P you just look at what x
is at any given instant of Time how does
it move well that's just projecting onto
the x-axis and it just moves back and
fourth it oscillates the oscillator
oscillates and it oscillates uh with
exactly this kind of motion it also
oscillates if you projected it onto the
P
axis right and notice when it's furthest
out in
X it's moving
fastest
no when it's furthest out in
X when it's furthest out in X it's
moving slowest why when it's way out
here at maximum x p is equal to
Z when it's up at its maximum X is equal
to zero so when the oscillator is far
out it's moving slow when it's close in
it's moving fast and you can think of
the two motions the X motion and the P
motion as the projection of the circular
phase space motion onto the x-axis and
onto the P
AIS
um phase
space is quite
fundamental notice some other things now
not all systems move on circles but all
systems do move on surfaces of constant
energy so when you write the energy
however you have to write it in terms of
X and
P then the trajectories in that X P
space are surfaces of constant energy
they're Contours of constant
energy of total energy the energy being
expressed in terms of X and
P there's another fact that's obvious
for this system well if you think about
it in terms of circles it's obvious for
this system but it's also very general
it's going to play a very very big role
in the structure of mechanics it's the
following fact supposing you take a
little patch of area in the phase
space this patch could stand for your
uncertainty in the knowledge of where
you begin you know that you begin
somewhere in here and that's all you
know what happens to it it just moves
around and around and around but the
most important thing is that it
preserves its
area area in Phase space is preserved
with time
I'm going to come back to that I'm a
little getting I'm reaching yeah I've
reached N9 o'clock and uh that's the end
of my
um energy so I my hamiltonian has run
out but
yeah
yeah yeah uh
right we need to be able to solve
where's our
equation we need to be able to solve for
x dots in terms of p in order if if we
want if our goal is to write things in
terms of p and
X right if that's our goal and we will
see that it will be our goal but if
that's our goal to rewrite mechanics in
terms of x's and PS we've got to
eliminate the X dots out of the problem
that means we've got to solve for the X
dots in terms of the p and plug back in
we can't do that unless uh unless
um that would that would present some
problems those L Grans are deemed to be
fundamentally sick and
uh um the
sickness I'll tell you we'll we'll do an
example or two remind me next week I'll
work out an example and you'll see what
goes wrong at the place where you can't
solve the equations for something
happens something happens it's bad the
the uh the motion doesn't make
[Music]
sense the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu